Guide to the Alice Bache Gould Papers ALBA.043
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Alice Bache Gould Papers
1937-1946
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Gould, Alice Bache, 1868-1953
ALBA.043
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Alice Bache Gould, scion of a distinguished New England family, Bryn Mawr graduate, and university teacher in the field of mathematics, became a pioneer scholar of the history of early exploration in the Caribbean, and particularly of Chistopher Columbus's voyages. She pursued this work in many libraries and archives, and spent much of the last forty years of her life in Spain. The collection consists of correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, her trustee in Boston. The letters, mostly written from Spain during the late 1930s and early 1940s, allude to Gould's financial circumstances, her travels and her social and scholarly pursuits.
Provenance
The Alice B. Gould papers were donated to the Spanish Civil War archives at Brandeis University by Augustus P. Loring, a nephew of Samuel Vaughn, in 1973. Additional letters were donated by Mr. Loring in 1985. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archive collections, formerly housed at Brandeis.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Alice Bache Gould was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1868, and was descended from several highly distinguished New England families. Her mother's family, the Quincy's had been prominent in Massachusetts affairs since before the Revolution, and her father, Benjamin Apthorp Gould, was a Harvard graduate and a well-known astronomer. Her independent means enabled her to travel widely in pursuit of her pioneering scholarly work, and also to pursue a number of philanthropic projects. She was raised in Quincy and was educated at the newly formed Bryn Mawr College, graduating in the class of 1889. She continued her education in mathematics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and the University of Chicago, and was hired as a faculty member in that field at Bryn Mawr. In 1903, after she discovered an important document about Barbados while in Puerto Rico, her scholarly interest changed from mathematics to the study of the earliest voyages of discovery across the Atlantic. In 1911, at age forty-three, she first traveled to Spain, where she visited the Archive of the Indies to investigate Christopher Columbus's route to Barbados. Fluent in Spanish, she was to spend seven years in Puerto Rico and most of four decades in Spain pursuing her interest in early exploration. She taught at a number of universities in the United States, endowed scholarship funds and left rich collections of research material to institutions in Spain and the U.S. Her work won high praise from Harvard historian Samuel Eliot Morison, and the Spanish government awarded her several prestigious honors. Perhaps her greatest accomplishment as a scholar was the compilation of the names and biographies of all the members of the crew of Columbus's first voyage.
After many visits to Spain in earlier years, Miss Gould traveled there in July 1939, apparently with the intention of settling permanently. Her letters, written from hotels in Seville, Valladolid and other Spanish locales, convey a vivid sense of the life of a relatively well-off American in pre-war and World War II-era Spain. The correspondence also records her contacts with Spanish government officials in the United States before 1939, and her views of Spanish life and affairs. A notable passage in a letter of May 1, 1939, recalls May Day demonstrations in Seville in May 1936 [mistakenly dated 1937 in the letter] in which the socialist and anarchist masses seemed to her "like wild beasts." Alice Bache Gould died on July 25, 1953 at her home in Simancas, Spain.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is arranged into one series of correspondence, mostly between Gould and her trustee Samuel Vaughn; most of the letters date from the period when she was living in Spain. The letters deal primarily with Gould's finances and with personal matters, and include much detail on expatriot life in Spain, especially during World War II.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Correspondence
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Alice Bache Gould Student Notes, Institute Archives and Special Collections, M.I.T. Libraries
Alice B. Gould Papers, Special Collections Department, Bryn Mawr College Library
Alice B. Gould Papers, Massachusetts Historical Society
Spain |x Description and Travel.; Quincy (Mass.); Simancas (Spain).; Correspondence.; Vaughn, Samuel; Gould, Alice Bache, 1868-1953
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Unidentified Correspondence, Jul 1937-Oct 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Aug 1937, Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jan 1938-Apr 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jan 1939-Apr 1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, May 1939-Jun 1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jul 1939-Sep 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Nov 1939-Dec 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jan 1940-Feb 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Mar 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Apr 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, May 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jul 1940-Oct 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Nov 1940-Dec 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jan 1941-Mar 1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Apr 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, May 1941 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jun 1941 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jul 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Aug 1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Sep 1941-Dec 1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Feb 1942-Mar 1942 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Apr 1942-Nov 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jan 1943 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Feb 1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jun 1943-Aug 1943 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jan 1944-May 1944 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Aug 1944 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Oct 1944 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Nov 1944 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Dec 1944 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Sep 1945-Oct 1945 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, Jan 1946 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence between Alice Bache Gould and Samuel Vaughn, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)